Bone Candy

GLEN COOK

THE CAMPAIGN SEASON WAS OVER. THE WEATHER STANK. THE DARK Horse was packed elbow to asshole. There wasn’t enough make-work to keep the troops busy. Markeg Zhorab’s wife and sister had to help him serve. The wicked of mind hoped he would bring out his delectable daughter.

Otto checked his last card, cursed. A turn as dealer had not helped. His luck was still dreadful. “You’re damned grim for a guy that keeps winning, Croaker.”

“Bad nightmare last night. Still feeling it.”

Silent signed, “Same one?”

“Third night in a row.”

Otto grinned. “Your honey must be missing you.” The old canard.

Silent signed, “Stop that.”

My turn. I pounced, down with eleven. Otto cursed. Silent shook his head, resigned. Corey, in One-Eye’s usual seat, pretended to wipe away tears. “When is the battlefield not a battlefield?”

“Huh?” Sergeant Otto grunted. “That some dumb-ass riddle?”

“One-Eye asked me that last time we talked.”

Silent was the only wizard in the tavern. I asked, “Where are Goblin and One-Eye?”

Their apprentice, the Third, was missing, too. He did not usually stray far from the beer. Those two can drive anyone to drink.

Otto collected Silent’s deal like he feared the cards would bite. “Them two are gone together, that could be bad.”

Those two wizards are always up to no good but not usually together. The table fell into a deep disquiet. Corey muttered, “Definitely not good.” Silent nodded grimly.

Zhorab delivered an untimely pitcher, muttered, “Flies.” He hustled off, loath to leave his bar undefended.

I discarded. Corey snagged the card, spread a five-six-seven-eight, but nobody groused. Everybody suddenly had a whole lot of nothing to discuss. Cards and drinks had become totally fascinating.

Two Dead stepped into the room. Long, lean, skeletal, he needed more legs and eyes to complete himself.

Otto murmured, “When is the battlefield not a battlefield?”

That could be more than one question depending on how you heard it.

* * *

Two Dead. Real name, Shor Chodroze, wizard colonel from Eastern Army HQ with plenipotentiary powers. A blessing upon the Black Company bestowed by the Taken Whisper. He never volunteered anything about his real mission. He was said to be an unpredictably nasty sociopath. Our main wizards disappeared right after he arrived. He was Two Dead because when he rolled in with one oversize bodyguard, all bluster and self-regard, the lieutenant had declared, “That man ain’t worth two dead flies.”

Otto dealt. The rest of us shrank. Somebody was about to get unhappy.

I met Two Dead’s gaze, as always amazed that he owned two good eyes. The left side of his face featured a lightning bolt of bruise-colored scar tissue, forehead to chin, but his eye had survived. I suspected a glancing upward thrust from an infantry pole arm.

He headed our way. And . . . something had him spooked. Not good, a sorcerer with the heebie-jeebies.

We were not the cause. He held us in abiding contempt. Still, he kept his bodyguard close. He knew his Company history.

Where was Buzzard Neck now?

Two Dead pointed at me, then Silent. “You two. Come with me. Bring your gear.”

I always lug a bag. You never know when some idiot will need sewing up.

* * *

Silent took two steps out into the street, stopped dead. I banged into his back. “Hey! None of your mime stuff!” He had picked up the hobby recently.

This was not that. This was a response to the weather.

A wind hummed in from the north, flinging snow pellets into our faces.

The chill did not bother Two Dead. Nor had he been drinking. The cold shock had me hungry to piss, but Two Dead barked, “Come!”

I came.

Buzz awaited us in full battle gear, including a great goofy old-time kite shield. His expression was pinched. He had obvious stomach troubles.

He was a house in boots. Guys like him usually end up being called Tiny or Little Whoever, and are dim, but this walking building was supernaturally quick, monster strong, and twice as smart as the creep who employed him.

He was Buzzard Neck because his neck was long and crooked and included an Adam’s apple like an Adam’s melon. The name quickly shrank to Buzz.

He never said much. He was as well-liked as Two Dead was well-loathed. He claimed to have survived some of the shit the Company had, including the Battle at Charm.

Two Dead headed out. We followed, me hoping I would not have to hold it long.

Technically, we could have told Two Dead to go pound sand. He was not in our chain of command. But he was tight with Whisper, and Whisper was hungry for excuses to pound the Company. Also, he might be a cat underfoot for a long time. Not to mention, I was really curious about what could give the spider wizard the jimjams.

* * *

Aloe sprawls without being big, though it is the grandest metropolis for a hundred miles. Two Dead led us a third of a mile, to the lee of a redbrick box on whitewashed limestone foundations.

“There.” He indicated a mound of brown fur in a dried-out flower patch. Wind stirred the fur and dead leaves.

I opined, “It don’t look healthy.”

Silent said nothing. Buzz clutched his gut.

I asked, “What is it?” Not a badger. It was too big and the color was wrong. Not a bear. It was too small.

“I don’t know,” Two Dead said. “It smells of sorcery.”

Silent nodded. Buzz looked desperate to take a squat.

I stepped left, relieved myself at last. Steam rose to meet randomly falling snowflakes. Fat flakes. It must be getting warmer.

I eased closer. The beast was curled up like a pill bug.

Two Dead said, “There were two others. They scooted when they saw us.”

Buzz said, “I didn’t see them.”

Two Dead said, “They ran a few steps and just faded out.” He was nervous all over again. How come?

I asked, “What did they look like?”

“Giant beavers or woodchucks? They were gone too quick to tell.”

Well. Beavers and groundhogs are somewhat less fierce than bears.

This one was not the right shade for a woodchuck. I didn’t know about giant beavers, though.

I noted a stir not caused by the wind.

Silent offered a sorcery alert.

Two Dead said, “Something magical is about to happen.” He did not mean magical in a wondrous surprise for the kids kind of way.

The moment disappointed. It expired without calamity.

I took a knee, faked veterinary skills.

The animal breathed slow and shallow and had a faint heartbeat. Hibernating? Some bears just drop in place when the sleepy season comes.

It didn’t waken and shred me. Two Dead took that as license to revert to his old obnoxious self.

* * *

Silent and I hauled the beast on Buzz’s shield. Buzz was too damned big to help. The downhill end had to carry most of the weight. Plus, he was having trouble keeping his trousers clean.

* * *

The beast sprawled on a table in my clinic. Two Dead perched like a spider on a stool close by, manfully keeping his yap shut. The captain and Otto were present as well. Like Two Dead, they kept quiet while the professional me worked. Buzz was off haunting a latrine.

“This is one ugly gob of snot,” the professional said. Stretched out it looked more like a baboon than a beaver. Its face was a fright mask of scarlet skin. It had teeth fit for a crocodile. Its eyes were snakelike. Each foot included semi-retractable claws and a stubby but opposable thumb.

“It’s starting to smell like a vulture’s breath,” Otto observed.

Its heart rate was rising, too. “The cold must have laid it down.” Our vile weather might not be all bad.

The captain jiggered the flue on my heating stove.

“Then these things shouldn’t be dangerous till the weather changes.” It would, local boy Corey had promised. We would see one more spring-like week before winter came to stay.

Otto prodded, “Croaker?” There was work to do. Critical work. The Old Man was here his own self.

Did they know something? Two Dead certainly wondered.

The Old Man was all fired-up curious. “It’s supernatural, right? What kind? Where from? Was it summoned? Is it invasive? Somebody talk to me.” He was sure that Two Dead was to blame.

Two Dead shook his head. “I promise, it’s new to me.”

“Where are Goblin and One-Eye? Anybody know?”

Otto said, “They ain’t been seen for days.”

I reminded, “The colonel says there were more of these things. Better find the others while it’s cold.”

Otto mused, “Warfare by elliptical means?”

“When is the battlefield not a battlefield?”

We had crushed the Rebel in the region, a success that troubled some “friends.” Vast incompetence and corruption had been turned up, which the guilty resented. Whisper’s own discomfort was why we had Two Dead as a guest.

I had hoped the Rebel survivors would slink away to recruit, to train, to collect weapons and supplies, and to wait for us to be transferred. Informants said that quiet season would never come. Senior Rebels wanted Aloe back. The Port of Shadows might be hidden here.

Aloens did not understand that echo out of deep time. Rebel insiders did. The honest ones got so scared they sometimes came over to us.

* * *

I read a lot. I root around in folklore, legend, and local history. Port of Shadows references a plot to resurrect the Dominator, lord of the old Domination. He is still a demigod to some. The Port of Shadows is a gateway he can use to escape his tomb.

Some Rebel chieftains are closet Resurrectionists. The Lady has been plagued by them since she escaped her own grave, leaving him behind.

The Old Man and his cronies are worried, but they do not confide in the Annalist. The Annalist writes things down.

Might this monster be a Resurrectionist tool? Our enemies had not yet gone supernaturally asymmetric. Sneaking lethal paranormal uglies into an enemy camp was more like something we would do.

The captain leaned in, tempting the beast. He asked Silent, “Have Croaker cut it up to look at its insides? Or cage it and wait?”

Silent shrugged. He was out of his element.

The captain asked Two Dead, “Suggestions, Colonel?” while looking for some subtle tell.

The beast had been the sorcerer’s discovery.

Two Dead remained unperturbed. He had come to us suspect. That would never change. “Let it live, but keep it cold. Find the others. Examine a healthy one.” He eyed Silent.

Silent shrugged again, stubbornly frugal with his opinions.

* * *

I bent close, combed fur, hunting vermin. Fleas, ticks, lice, all tell tales. “This thing is getting warmer . . .” I reeled back, shoved by Silent. He pointed. Flakes of obsidian ash had puffed out of a nostril. “Hand me a sample bottle.” Then, “Make that a bunch.”

A black beetle stomped into the light, as shiny as the flakes. It glared around, measuring the world for conquest.

The Old Man asked, “That some kind of scarab?”

A second bug marched out, bumped into the first. Number one was in a bad mood. Bam! No threat display. No ritual dance. The bugs started trying to murder one another with ridiculous bear-trap jaws.

I whined, “Anybody got any idea what the hell?”

Nope. Two Dead, though, did snag my biggest glass jar, which he shoved over the beast’s head. He packed the gaps with handy rags.

Otto took off in a big hurry, leaving the door halfway open. Snow blew in before Silent shut it.

Black flakes presaged the emergence of more beetles. These were not immediate bugacidal maniacs. They just wanted to leave. The jar frustrated their ambitions.

Then they went berserk. “What a racket.” The captain was rattled, something you seldom saw.

The host animal began to deflate. Two Dead stuffed more bandages. A few beetles, struck brilliant, snipped cloth chunks with those nasty jaws.

“We need a container big enough for the whole thing,” Two Dead said. “Maybe a pickle barrel.”

Bam! Otto came back lugging a big tin box with a latch-down top that hailed from the commissary, where it kept grain and flour free of vermin.

“Perfect,” Two Dead declared, nonplussed. This was too-quick thinking by people he wanted to be too dull to notice him nudging them onto a hangman’s trap.

Otto said, “Push it in, glass and all.” He positioned the tin so Two Dead could shove the beast in.

Two Dead held his paws up like a dog begging. He should soil his delicate fingers?

“Really?” the Old Man barked. “Push the damned thing!”

A particularly formidable beetle chose that moment to make his getaway via the beast’s nether orifice. A Two Dead finger was nearby. It took a bite. Two Dead howled, “Oh, shit! Gods damn, that hurts!”

An even studlier bug tromped forth as the beast flopped forward. It had even more ridiculous jaws and a back end like a long, thin funnel. It flew at Two Dead, literally, wing cases flung high, ladybug style. It landed on the back of the sorcerer’s left hand, grabbed hold, took a hearty bite. Then it stood on its nose, curled its tail down, drove its tip into the wound.

All that took only an eye-blink to happen. Two Dead shrieked again.

Silent crunched the bug.

Otto pounded the lid onto the can. The monster left several wriggling grubs on the table. The Old Man chased escaped beetles. Silent and I wrestled Two Dead into a chair. He began to shake. Shock? The bites did not look that bad. Silent hand signed, “It laid eggs.”

The sealed tin sang like a metal roof in a hailstorm.

The Old Man killed one last fugitive bug, turned on the grubs. “Otto, take the can to the trash pit. Then get every swinging dick out looking for the other two animals. Hire tracking dogs.” He moved over to watch as I dug almost invisibly tiny cream-color beads out of Two Dead’s hand.

Otto left with the singing biscuit tin. And busted back in half a minute later. “Look what I found sneaking around with a sack of stolen bread and bacon.” He had our apprentice sorcerer, the Third, by the scruff of the neck.

The kid was not happy. Truth be, he had had few shots at happiness since he got tangled up with Goblin and One-Eye.

The Old Man settled into a chair, leaned back, considered the Third. He put on his “I’m eager to hear how you’ll try to bullshit me on this” face.

Silent passed me a jar of carbolic. I put bug eggs in, then dribbled liquid onto Two Dead’s wounds. He squealed.

The Third volunteered, “One-Eye sent me to fetch food.”

Really? That little shit is not big on bacon. On the other hand, the Third would devour it by the hog side.

I worked on Two Dead. Silent watched grubs in a jar. They behaved no better than adults. The Old Man glared at the Third. The level of noise outside rose. Otto had relayed the captain’s orders.

Buzz stumbled in looking like death warmed over. His sojourn in the latrine had not helped much.

The Third said, “I was getting stuff for me. Otto spotted me before I started on One-Eye’s stuff.”

I observed, “The kid has his priorities straight.”

Two Dead managed a ghost smile. His shakes continued.

The Old Man grumped, “Watch the colonel till you’re sure he’ll be all right. We don’t hand Whisper any fresh excuses. You.” He poked the Third. “You’re with me.”

Buzz wanted to fuss over his boss. Two Dead growled, “You look like a man with the drizzling shits, Tesch. Smell like one, too.” He poked me with his unbitten hand. “I’ll live. Help him.”

I thought Buzz must have drunk some bad water. He ought to know better. I loaded him with liquids and orders not to stray far from the latrine. He was unhappy about not being able to stick close to Two Dead.

“Yet here you are alive and recuperating,” I observed after Two Dead suggested that the Company might have rigged all this. “You probably conjured those animals yourself and just accidentally got the bad end.”

That was plain chin music, ridiculousness in exchange for absurdity, but Two Dead found something curious there. Like was he supposed to get it with the rest of us?

I was tempted to pin a target on Whisper’s back. The more discord at HQ the less time those people would have to harass us out here.

I reiterated the common remark: “When is the battlefield not a battlefield?”

Two Dead eyed me. “An intriguing question, physician. Worth considering here, in these troubled times.” He cocked his head, listened. I caught a vague hint of distant wind chimes. That rattled me. It tied into my recurrent nightmare somehow. “I’m going to lie down and brood on it.” Two Dead indicated a cot.

* * *

I was snuggled into a cot and blankets myself. The captain poked me. “What’s wrong with him?” Head jerk toward Two Dead, on his back, on his cot. Drool glistened on his ugly cheek. Snot hung from the nostril on that side. Dead sexy.

“What time is it?”

“Nighttime. We got the other beasts. What about Chodroze?”

“He was his old ugly self when I laid down.” I set my feet on the cold dirt floor, rose with a groan, toddled over. Our chatter had not awakened Two Dead.

I felt the heat before I touched him.

The Captain said, “The dogs found them, unconscious from the cold. The men tinned them up and threw them in the fire pit.”

“We need to pack Two Dead with snow. He’s burning up.”

“Whatever. Keep him healthy.”

Two Dead had a weak, fast, irregular pulse and a dangerous fever. “I’ll need help cooling him down.” I started stripping him. That did not waken him. “What did the Third have to say?”

The Old Man looked like he had bitten into a chunk of alum candy.

Goblin and One-Eye were up to something. And he might not entirely disapprove.

Dead fierce, he snagged a bucket and headed outside. The weather had turned enthusiastically blizzardy.

He returned with a pail of muddy snow.

I indicated Two Dead’s wounded arm. Scarlet threads ran up it from the uglier wound.

“Blood poisoning?”

“Some kind of poisoning. Blood poisoning isn’t usually so aggressive.”

Skin flexed near Two Dead’s worst wound. I had not gotten every egg.

“Help me get him on the table. I’ll clear the wound. You pack him with snow. Start with his head and throat. We need to cool his brain.”

Move made. Snow packed and melting onto the floor to make mud. I dug with a scalpel. The Old Man hauled more snow.

* * *

“How about we just dump him in a snowdrift?”

“I need light to work.” I had excised two thin grubs. They writhed in an alcohol bath. I was after what I hoped was the last.

“Those bitty things caused the blood poisoning?”

“Their shit is probably toxic.”

“Ugly.”

“Life is.” In some forms, ugly for lots of us.

I fit puzzle pieces while I worked, hoping I was fooling myself, but afraid I was looking chaos in the crimson, googly eye.

“How come the tourniquet?”

“Keeping the poison contained. To avoid amputation if I can.”

“That wouldn’t be good.”

No. “I should ask what he wants, worst case, but he won’t wake up.”

“We need more hands. Maybe Silent can get to him.”

“I can’t go. Where the hell is Buzz?”

“Buzz is in his rack, down and out and soaked in shit. He’d be dead if you hadn’t given him that tea. Poor Corey is babysitting. I’ll get another bucket, then head out on a recruiting tour.”

So. Old Buzz came down with the drizzling shits right when his principal started dying from an infestation of supernatural parasites. That wanted a closer look. The timeline might tell us when Buzz picked up what was trying to kill him. Also, maybe who was there when it happened.

I winkled the last worm out. The Old Man brought more snow. I mused, “When is the battlefield not a battlefield?”

The captain eyed me oddly, shrugged, took off with his trained-bear shuffle.

The day’s puzzle might have an explanation hidden inside the recurring question. That might put me eyeball to eyeball with a repellant cousin question that could have multiple readings as well. “When is my enemy not an enemy?”

* * *

Otto and his pal Hagop turned up. The captain had caught them trying to sneak off to town to help Markeg Zhorab get a little bit richer. They hauled snow.

We did not see the captain again right away. He went and stole a short nap. When he did turn up he had the Third in tow, all decorated with light shackles. “He’s all we got. Silent is missing now, too.”

The Third shook his wild shock of curls, lost in the insanities.

Answers had to wait. Two Dead was not improving. Snow packs were not enough. I told the Third, “I need the colonel awake. We need to talk. Amputation may be his only salvation. I can’t decide that for him.”

“Why bother? We could get shot of him.”

“I save whoever I can.” Not that I have not made exceptions. Not that Two Dead was insufficiently despicable to make the “he needs killing” list. “And he’s Whisper’s pet.”

“Don’t smell like that special a relationship to me.” The Third eyed Two Dead. “It’ll be tough. Feels like Silent put him in a coma for the pain.”

“You can’t bring him out?”

“Didn’t say that. Said it’s gonna be tough. Get ready for some serious screaming. His arm is gonna feel like it’s on fire.”

“Hang on then.” I slathered Two Dead’s forearm with topical painkiller. “All right. Go.”

* * *

Two Dead surprised us. He did not let the pain unhinge him. He was creepy normal, disinclined to shed any limbs unnecessarily.

He was short four already, you asked me.

“I won’t do it casually,” I promised.

He was caught in a cleft stick. I had no reason to wish him well, but he did realize that I would not just maim him when death by inattention would be so much easier.

He played through the pain. “If it’s the best choice, do it.” His speech slurred. I kept feeding him painkiller tea.

The captain talked to him steadily, gently, casually, like he was Two Dead’s cousin. He wanted to slide inside the sorcerer’s head while he was addled.

I set up to cut, ever more sure that it could not be avoided. I listened. Two Dead made no sense. He was old, hardcore, and stubborn. The Old Man was unlikely to get much.

Then he did get something that I missed. He buttoned up and hit the weather and was gone for fifteen minutes.

I got Two Dead strapped down. The Third whined, “Can I go? I don’t want to see this.”

“You’re going to be Company, you’d better get used to blood.” Which sparked memories I would rather not have recalled. I have eaten a lot of bone candy with the Company.

* * *

There was no choice. Two Dead’s body could not resist the poison. “Sorry, Colonel.” Our senior sorcerers might have helped, but they were unavailable. Best not mention that. Two Dead supposedly had a fecund bent for paranoid violence.

He glared at the Third. The Third said, “I am sorry, sir. I’ll do my best, but medical sorcery isn’t among my skills.”

Pain kept Two Dead from helping himself.

I asked the captain, “How goes the search for our favorite duo?”

“Still missing.” He eyed Two Dead like he suspected a connection.

I asked, “Go ahead, Colonel? Final decision time.”

Two Dead nodded grimly, probably rehearsing cruelties he would visit on those who had brought him to this, deliberately or otherwise.

“Would you like to remain awake during the procedure?”

“Put me out. Tesch won’t shit himself forever. Anything goes wrong, he’ll see that I don’t walk the road to Hell by myself.”

I smelled bluster and some graveyard sneaking-past, whistling.

“As you wish, sir.” I soaked a bandage with pale green fluid. “Third, hold this over his face. Lightly! He has to breathe it.”

The patient went under in seconds. “Third, Captain, watch me close in case there are questions later.”

The Third narrowly avoided messing himself. He got the subtext.

I started. I talked while I worked. “Do Goblin and One-Eye being missing have anything to do with our beetle-infested weasels?”

No reply.

“There is something going on. I’m not blind.”

“They could be up to something illegal,” the captain said, carefully. “More likely, though, you’re seeing something just because you want to.”

The Third protested, “They were just trying to get the straight skinny on Two Dead and Buzzard Neck. They aren’t what you think. Goblin knows Buzz from the Battle at Charm.”

I suffered a half-ass flashback to my nightmare. It did not affect my work. That was old, familiar labor. I could hack off a limb while dead drunk or ready to collapse from exhaustion.

The captain shrugged. He was playing it close.

When is the battlefield not a battlefield? The enemy of my enemy is what and who?

When did those two wizards turn invisible? Right after Two Dead showed up. Because of Buzz? Was he more than just Two Dead’s lifeguard?

All this drama, and our empire still controls half the world.

The Lady loves the chaos. While her underlings are backstabbing and undercutting each other they are too busy to move on her. She can focus on keeping her husband underground.

* * *

The Old Man wakened me again. “Going to sleep your life away?” He did not roll out the old saw about sleeping all I wanted after I was dead. He made a hand sign. Four men shifted Buzz from a litter to a table.

I asked, “What was that?”

“What was what?”

“Thought I heard wind chimes. Really faint.”

“Maybe you’re still dreaming.”

Crap! I had been. The nightmare. The Lady was in there with somebody who moved in wind-chime tinkle . . . Was it a dream? Or something from the Tower? She does touch me strangely, at the oddest of times.

No matter. I was awake now. It was gone, and what was happening in the waking world seemed less rational than any dream. I had cooked up a fresh stew of weird ideas while I was off in slumberville.

I had a client. “Couldn’t you clean him up before you brought him in? I’ll need a month to air the place out.”

Buzz might have been belly up now if I had not worked on him earlier. His situation was that grim.

Corey had helped bring Buzz in. The kid was dead on his feet. “I tried to keep him hydrated, but whatever I put in the top end came out the bottom like there was a pipe straight through.”

“Let me check some stuff.”

Buzz’s pulse was fast and feeble. His temperature was fierce. I peeled back an eyelid. His pupil was a pinpoint. That did not add up. I smelled his breath, risky even when a patient is healthy considering the general disdain for hygiene. I said, “Poke.” Surprised.

That raised me a crop of blank looks.

“It’s everywhere. Big, waxy-leafed plant. Has shiny purple berries in bunches kind of like grapes. Nasty hard on your gut. Alkaloid. But they taste so bad you shouldn’t be able to choke enough down to do this.”

Corey asked, “So how did he get past the first mouthful?”

That would be the question. “I’ve never actually seen poke poisoning, but I’m sure this is it. Maybe it started out as something else. He didn’t smell like poke before. There are stains on his lips that weren’t there before. Somebody forced the juice down him.” He must have been dead unconscious. Even a groggy Buzzard Neck would be hard to force.

I saw nobody looking so innocent he must be guilty, but the question was less who than why. Nobody hated Buzz.

Was the point to eliminate Two Dead’s protection?

* * *

I set Buzz up so we could dump fluids in as fast as they left. I turned sleepy again. The captain observed. The Third assisted me, sort of. Corey snored his lungs out on a cot I wanted for me. Two Dead barely breathed on, awash in painkillers.

The Old Man asked, “You had a good dream? That why you want to get back to sleep?”

All I had left was a lingering nostalgia. “It was something about the Lady and the Tower.”

“You don’t usually dream about her, do you?”

I was once a prisoner in the Tower. I spent a lot of time around the Lady then, and that has cost me years of merciless teasing.

“I don’t. No. Why?”

“Maybe she was trying to tell you something.”

“Maybe,” I admitted, reluctantly. The Lady randomly and wickedly flings fuel into the fire by contacting me.

“Remember what you can while there’s something to recall.”

“Too late, boss. It’s gone. Only . . . Buzz was in it somewhere. He had on a smiley mask.”

“Really? And us without a wizard to hypnotize you.”

He wanted the Lady to have sent me a dream. “If Goblin was here, we could make him channel her.” Goblin could provide an occasional direct link, letting the Lady use his mouth. That was rough on him, but I did not mind. It made for less strain on me. And he does not get accused of inappropriate fraternization when she uses him.

Two Dead groaned. The knockout painkillers were wearing off. I checked his dressing. “I’ve had the same nightmare every night since the wizards disappeared.”

“But didn’t say anything even though she was in there.”

“Because she was in them.”

“Yes. Let us not deliver live ammunition into the hands of anyone who might taunt us. Is there a connection?”

“Maybe.” I had had no such suspicion before. We all dream. Sometimes we have nightmares. Those seldom make sense, the little we recall. I had never thought mine meant anything special. Now I got it. She had wanted to tell me something, but I would not listen.

It had been a busy double dozen hours since Zhorab whispered “Flies,” the hours fat with events boasting an almost dreamlike lack of dynamic structure.

Two Dead lapsed into a deeper sleep after I applied another pad soaked green.

* * *

The door opened. Cold and snow and Otto burst in to bellow, “Look what I caught me this time.”

He had a groggy Goblin by the scruff. The little toad sagged there, cross-eyed, his pupils not right. “What’s wrong with him?”

“I thumped him some to make him cooperate. He maybe has a little concussion.”

Some folks find Goblin or One-Eye getting thumped a blessed notion.

The wizard rasped, “He didn’t have no call to attack me. I was on my way here anyways.”

Nobody swallowed that.

The captain demanded, “Where you been? And why? Take into consideration my current lack of tolerance for your customary bullshit.”

I checked Buzz again, then moved in on Goblin.

His eyes uncrossed. His little turd brain began to function, sort of. “The Lady touched me.” He gave me an ugly look. “I was happy out there in my cave. But here she came because her honey bear was always asleep or drunk when she tried to get with him. I run off because when Chodroze turned up I remembered his sidekick from Charm. Him and me went eye to eye and claw to claw back then.”

Buzz was on the other side, then? Not a window-rattling reveal. Others had shifted allegiance in preference to getting dead, Whisper herself included. I had helped set her up. She has nurtured an unreasonable animosity ever since.

Goblin said, “I needed privacy. I had to dip into the demon realms to winkle out the truth.”

The Old Man made an impatient “Come on!” gesture.

“I also wanted out of sight so Tesch wouldn’t remember me. Back then he was called Essentially Capable Shiiraki, the Spellsmith.”

I remembered that odd name. “I thought he went into the mass grave with all the other Rebel wizards.”

“His family thought so. But I found a surviving familiar who knew the true story. Adequately motivated, it barfed up the details.”

“Adequately motivated?” the Old Man asked.

“I told it I wouldn’t report it to the Lady. Seeing as how it had gotten dragged into the Tower after the fighting, it wasn’t inclined to go back.”

I understood that sentiment.

“What is going on?” the Old Man demanded. “You having had a heart-to-heart with this friendly devil.”

“It’s complicated and insane. Chodroze believes he was sent here to see if we’ve found the Port of Shadows thing. He is supposed to destroy it if he can. Messing with us was bonus fun. But Tesch had a darker mission. He was supposed to kill Chodroze and frame the Company for it. And get control of the Port of Shadows if it’s real. Not to destroy it. And he had orders to take out the Company leadership if the chance presented itself.”

I blurted, “Buzz was supposed to murder Two Dead?”

“Chodroze must’ve made Whisper really unhappy.”

Two Dead was a long-time favorite of Whisper’s. “She is one vindictive bitch.”

She had loathed the world with smoldering fury since the moment she had become Taken. Taking made her one of the most powerful beings on earth but a slave of the Lady as well.

My drowsiness fled. “Two Dead might be the good guy? Buzz might be the villain?” Everything I had worked out must be wrong. “Where does One-Eye fit?”

The captain leaned in, daring Goblin to be less than completely forthright.

“I don’t know anymore. He stuck with me at the start, but he grabbed his poison sack and took off when Tesch called up the infested chinkami. He knew what they were. Don’t ask me how. The little turd knows way too much shit that nobody ought to. He said we would be in the shit really deep after the cold weather broke. That’s the last we saw of him.”

The captain asked, “You got that from the Lady?”

“Mostly I figured it out myself. She only touched me because her honey wouldn’t listen. Going to suck to be you, Croaker. Your woman ain’t happy.” He grinned, showing teeth in desperate need of cleaning.

Why worry? She was weather. I would suffer through. “Instructive, though, eh? Her knowing what’s going on out here when she’s denned up a thousand miles away?” Some of us have trouble remembering what she can do.

The Old Man observed, “What is instructive is that while she sees every sparrow fall she mainly just lets them go plop! People like Whisper keep digging deeper holes by going right on pulling stupid tricks. They’ll cry hard when she finally brings the hammer down.”

That was long-winded for him. Remarkable things must be happening inside his head.

He fixed Goblin with his hard stare. “Tell me again, magic munchkin. Where is One-Eye? What is he up to?” He gestured. Otto moved over to wrangle the Third when the questioning turned to him. “What’s the blowback likely to be once HQ hears that Buzz and Two Dead screwed the pooch?”

Goblin shuffled. “Some major ass-covering. Tesch will turn out to be some deep-cover Rebel mole. Chodroze was always a loose ballista who let personal grudges color his judgment. It will be all our fault, somehow.”

I observed, “Same old, same old. How about if they both survive? Will that shift the battlefield under everybody’s feet?”

“You pull them through, we could see some wicked real excitement on down the road. She might even show an interest.”

The captain said, “We are the cow flop she uses to distract the flies out here.”

Yes. Our big boss was running a long con. This was another knot in the cord. I said, “I will save them.”

“Standing around with your thumb in your ass?” The Old Man turned to Otto. “Have him show you where he was supposed to take that food.” He indicated the Third. “One-Eye will be there. Hurt him if you have to but don’t break him. I want him helping Croaker. Goblin. You’re Croaker’s boy until Buzz and Two Dead are healthy enough to dance at his wedding.”

* * *

Otto and crew found One-Eye snoozing in a derelict shack on the edge of town. They got his head in a sack and his hands tied before he could bark. Nobody came out of it needing splints or stitches.

The Old Man was in a foul temper. He stood back, iron gaze fixed while One-Eye received the Word. The little black man wasted no time getting his shit together. “Focus on Shiiraki. We can’t do anything more for Chodroze except maybe add a slider spell to fight infection.”

“Goblin did that. Laid on a sleeper, too. Corey can handle him. You fed Buzz poke juice?”

“After the firenz he got in some wine he thought would help with the shits. You can’t taste firenz in sweet wine. It just gives you a stronger buzz. Blackberry is the best.”

And was the same color as poke juice. “The juice disguised the real poison?”

“Yep. He got drunk. Did a major stupid. He was already messed up with the shits.” Not exactly confessing. He ransacked my medicine stocks while he talked. “Here it is.” He held up a phial of dirty brown powder. “This will neutralize the firenz. The poke will take care of itself, you put enough liquid through.”

I did not know what firenz was. A poison, clearly. As Goblin did note, One-Eye knew a lot that nobody should. Came of being older than dirt, mostly.

The Old Man reminded One-Eye, “They need to pull through. The Tower is watching. The Tower wants it to happen.”

Wind chimes sang on cue, louder than ever. Everyone heard, not just the poor crazy Annalist. A lightning-bug flash in a corner turned into an expanding O-ring of sparkle. It reached a foot and a half in diameter. A dark-haired, to-die-for beautiful brunette teen looked out at us. She smiled a smile that lighted up the universe. She winked at me and pursed her lips in an air kiss that I would hear about forever. Then she faded without saying a word, leaving a tinkle, a hint of lilac, an impression that someone had watched from behind her, and a message clearly delivered to her favorite band of bad boys.

“Oh, my!” One-Eye blurted because the Lady had considered him directly and deliberately before flirting with me.

He had to improve his sense of discipline. And he would. For a while. But he was, is, and always will be One-Eye. He cannot be anything else.

He bustled around Buzz with Goblin and the Third helping. I decided to step outside. I had been too long safe from clean air.

It was daytime out there, still not thirty hours since Zhorab whispered “Flies.” Snow no longer fell, but the wind remained busy. It was warmer. The ground had begun to turn to mud. The world felt changed. Definitely not new but forever changed.

The captain joined me. “I don’t know what’s happened, but we have stumbled into a fresh new future.”

“It’s that line. When is the battlefield not a battlefield? We’ll win one big time without lifting a blade if those two survive.”

“When.”

“Yes, sir. When.”

“A handy friend, Two Dead. He’s almost Taken caliber but less subject to outside control. Buzzard Neck could be a useful badass, too.”

“We should seduce them.”

“We keep them alive, they’re ours. She is counting on us, Croaker. Stuff like this is going to keep happening. When is the enemy not an enemy? When it’s your friend patting your back with one hand while sticking a dagger in with the other.”

“I’d best get back in there and supervise.” It would not be impossible for One-Eye to precipitate a lethal mishap if there was something he thought needed hiding.

“Yes. No doubt One-Eye already thinks he sees some clever way to turn himself a profit.” The Old Man clasped my left shoulder, touching me directly for only the third or fourth time in all the years we have known one another. “You played your part well. Go win us a brace of new magicians.”

Yes. So. No direct confession, but . . . He had been part of a scheme with roots in the Tower. Somehow. Maybe he was the one romancing the crone.

“I’m on it, boss.”